Muhammad Aziz

Chakwal, Punjab, Pakistan +92 3135237774 engr.muhammadaziz96@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/zeezeee96 twitter.com/zeezeee96 github.com/zeezeee96

A mechanical engineer whose engine pumps JavaScript now. I'm a community-taught developer with over 4 years of working with HTML, JavaScript and React.Js frameworks for developing dynamic websites and having creative analytical and strong communication skills. As an engineer, I take challenges heads on and love solving complex problems.

Experience

OCTOBER 2021 - PRESENT

MERN Stack Developer / Pursue Today, Remote

- Shifted an old Ecommerce app from old Reactjs to Nextjs.
- Optimized Product details and listing page as server side, rest pages are static pages with dynamic pages as static site regeneration.
- Created Listing page with multiple type filters from Contentful and Backend.
- Implemented Context API for state management.
- Updated all page's designs with reusable styled components.
- Added 360 images on product page with zoom enabled on 360 photos.
- Created Responsive designs for 6-dimension widths.
- Custom reusable Modals and Responsive Sidebar using styled components.
- Integrated Contentful CMS for blogs and homepage content management, Added generic utility to use all those hompage content types on any required page and it can be controlled through contentful.
- Added unit tests for the whole app.
- Optimized the new site performance and SEO, extensively used Nextjs Image and script component.
- Added Custom Validations with React Hook Form.
- Added Secure Checkout Process with multi sections and auto credit card inputs with validations.
- Added flow and unit testing for a GraphQL backend.
- Created tiny utilities Like Image utility, services utility for APIs, local storage actions utility etc.

JANUARY 2021 - SEPTEMBER 2021

Front-End Developer / Gap Inc, Remote

Performed shopping bag optimization tasks of E-Commerce Clothing store app including logs
creation for every outgoing browser request and incoming response, saving logs to splunk,
creating alerts and emails in case some specified event occurs in log, code-refactoring, creating
multiple loyalty service flags, testing Loyalty program outcomes and other team members PRs.

MERN Stack Developer / Heapware, Remote

- Developed a Real Estate Property app with two modules of admin and user. and with property creations, property approving by admin, available properties, media uploading and their interactions, adding other users as friend, notifications and user's chats using Next.js. Also, deployed the app to Vercel and AWS amplify.
- Developed Clinical Practitioner app with 4 different modules of admin, agent, doctor, patient, with appointments for video call and in-clinic appointments, appointment approval, online prescriptions, online medicine facility, online lab tests, labs and pharmacy additions and approvals, blogs creations and user chat support.

Education

[2014-2018]

B.SC Mechanical Engineering/ UET Lahore

• CGPA 3.52/4

Soft Skills

- Critical Thinking
- Self-Analysis
- Leadership
- Adaptability

- Teamwork
- Developer Experience
- Flexibility
- Communication

Technical Skills

- JavaScript frameworks (React, Nextjs)
- Databases (MongoDB)
- CSS frameworks (MUI, Tailwind, Bootstrap, Ant-Design, Styled Components)
- Google Maps
- Contentful CMS

- Performance Optimization (SSR, ISR, SSG)
- Backend architecture (Express, Nodejs)
- JavaScript, TypeScript
- Socket.io
- JWT Authentications
- Magic 360

Personal Projects

Weather Search App/ (React, Axios, AccuWeatherAPI, MaterialUI)

Used MaterialUI library for React components. Added autocomplete city name search, search by location feature and auto display of 10 cities weather on homepage. Detail page shows the further details for that city weather. App is deployed on Netlify and displays real time data fetched from accuweather API.

Student Record Maintenance App/ (React, Axios, MongoDB, Express)

Worked with React Components and added read, add, delete and update functionality to records and save data to MongoDB via Nodejs and Express. Axios was used to handle API requests.

Truck Transport App / (React, Styled Components, MUI5, Google Maps)

Created responsive Trucks shipment app for creating shipments, adding drivers and trucks, tracking shipments live with user module.

Al SAAS App / (Next.js 13, Tailwind, Open Al, PayPal)

Integrated PayPal payment service to already build Al-SAAS application. Created PayPal Subscriptions and added monthly payments. Integrated subscription creation and expiration with Prisma DB.